All right, ready? בוקר טוב *Boker tov*. Today's דף *daf* is זיין
*Zayin*. We are in the middle of a discussion which is only
somewhat related to תמורה tmurah. *Temurah*, which is the question about sanctifying
animals, the prohibition not to sanctify as a קרבן korban *korban* animals
with a blemish. So it's similar in that, you know, it's a
sanctity you should not be doing, in which takes effect regardless. And
actually we will explicitly reference תמורה Tmura. *Temurah* in a little bit.
We pick up on the bottom of ו עמוד ב *vav amud
bet* and we have the following.
Where are we? Okay. So the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, טעמא דכתב קרא *ta'ama de-katav kra*. So it
is seven lines from the bottom, the line begins with the word
דכתב *de-katav*. So one of the דרשות drashot, *drashot* that we had
showed us that was a דרשה drasha *drasha* that the prohibition to
sanctify as a קרבן korban *korban* something which is blemished includes not
only קרבן korban *korban* that are brought in the בית המקדש Beit
HaMikdash, *Beit HaMikdash*, but even the שעיר המשתלח se'ir hamishtaleach. *Se'ir HaMishtale'ach*,
even the goat that is sent off the cliff. And the reason
is obvious. It's something that even if not brought in the בית
המקדש Beit HaMikdash *Beit HaMikdash* is supposed to be unblemished, although we
will sort of discuss that in a second. And therefore there is
an equal prohibition to sanctify it if it is blemished.
But one of the things is that at the moment that it's
sanctified, it should be able to go either way.
Well, that's exactly what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is about to address.
So let's take a look. So טעמא דכתב קרא *ta'ama de-katav kra*,
so the reason that it is forbidden to sanctify the שעיר המשתלח
*Se'ir HaMishtale'ach* if it's blemished is because the פסוק pasuk *pasuk* is
explicit. טעמא דכתב קרא *ta'ama de-katav kra* להשם L'Hashem, *la-Hashem*, that extra
word להשם L'Hashem *la-Hashem* which is coming to include this. הוא דלא
מייתי שעיר משתלח *hu de-lo mayti Se'ir Mishtale'ach*. That's why you cannot
bring a שעיר משתלח *Se'ir Mishtale'ach* that has a blemish. הא לא
רבי Rebbi קרא *ha lo rabi kra* להשם L'Hashem *la-Hashem*, had it
not said that, הוה אמינא havaminah שעיר משתלח בעל מום ba'al mum,
שפיר דמי *hava amina Se'ir Mishtale'ach ba'al mum shapir dami*, that it
would have been okay. So בכדי *bikhdi*, one minute, how could that
have been? אין הגורל קובע אלא בדבר הראוי *ein ha-goral kove'a ela
be-davar ha-ra'uy*. You can only have the drawing of the lots for
the two goats if both animals could be brought as the קרבן
korban, *korban*, right? You have to have the option of either one
winning, you know, the lottery and becoming the one that is brought
as the קרבן korban *korban* להשם L'Hashem *la-Hashem*. So how could I
have thought that you bring one that has a blemish and say,
oh well no worries, that's the שעיר המשתלח *Se'ir HaMishtale'ach*, that's not
a קרבן korban *korban*? But it has to be fit for being
brought as a קרבן korban *korban*. Now, just because that's true, you
might have said that you're not transgressing, you would have known it
had to be unblemished, but you would not necessarily have known that
you transgress the negative prohibition. But maybe the point is that look,
one of them was blemished, then the whole procedure would have been
invalid. So the whole way it's sort of, you know, so maybe,
you know, maybe somehow that saying that you'll never get there. But
it's still not exactly clear to me because, you know, why you
can't say the פסוק pasuk *pasuk* is coming to say that you
still have transgressed. Nevertheless, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is saying even without
the פסוק pasuk, *pasuk* I would have known you can't use it
because it has to be able to be the one that's להשם
L'Hashem *la-Hashem*. So let's see how the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* answers this.
אמר רב יוסף *Amar Rav Yosef*, yes,
also I mean there's a like a level of it for the
purification of our sins. Right, wouldn't you want to bring something that's
not blemished?
Yeah, clearly. But the point is you wouldn't have known, yes, I
mean there's an intuitive reason why, but you know that's probably what,
you know, why the prohibition does apply there. But the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* is just saying technically, legally, I would have known that it
would have been excluded regardless. So I didn't need an extra פסוק
pasuk *pasuk*. Now again, my question is the פסוק pasuk *pasuk* is
not just saying it's not valid, the פסוק pasuk *pasuk* is saying
that you transgress. But somehow the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* still feels that
the emphasis here was that without the פסוק pasuk. *pasuk* I might
have actually, I might have thought, meaning the implication of the דרשה
drasha *drasha* is that without the פסוק pasuk *pasuk* I might have
thought that it is valid if it's blemished. And that's why I
would have thought you don't transgress because maybe it's not invalid. And
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says that you're right, intuitively you would have
wanted it to be unblemished, but it would not, you would have
not known it legally. And the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is saying but
legally I would have known it because it has to be fit
to be the one that's להשם L'Hashem. *la-Hashem*. So let's take a
look. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this. אמר רב יוסף
*Amar Rav Yosef*, הא מני חנניה המצרי Chananya HaMitzri היא *haman Hananya
HaMitzri hi*. This is חנניה המצרי *Hananya HaMitzri*, דאמר אפילו דם בכוס
Afilu dam b'kos, מעכב חבירו משתפך לו *de-amar afilu dam be-kos me'akev
chaveiro mishtafek lo*. So there's interesting debates in יומא *Yoma*, what happens
if in the middle of all the procedures something happens to one
of the animals? So let's say, you know, you the one one
is להשם L'Hashem *la-Hashem*, one is לעזאזל L'Azazel *la-Azazel*, you set the
one that's לעזאזל L'Azazel. *la-Azazel* aside, you slaughter the one that's להשם
*la-Hashem* and you take the blood and you sprinkle it inside the,
you know, inside the Holy of Holies and all of that. Let's
say while you're waiting to do that, the the one that's supposed
to go לעזאזל L'Azazel *la-Azazel* dies on you. So what do you
do? Do you have to now go ahead and do the whole
procedure again from the beginning and take two and slaughter, you know,
slaughter the other one and so on? Can you keep the blood
that's already waiting and just get another one? So חנניה המצרי *Hananya
HaMitzri* says yeah, yeah, you don't have to redo it, just get
another one basically saying okay, this is the שעיר *Se'ir*, the blood
is the blood and let's keep on going. Okay, so according to
him, there could be a scenario where you don't have to be,
it doesn't have to be fit for being the one להשם *la-Hashem*,
right, where you're just replacing the dead one, you know the new
one that you're bringing is going... only to be לעזאזל. L'Azazel. So
therefore maybe it can have a blemish and maybe you wouldn't transgress.
So that's the scenario. אפילו דם בכוס, even if the blood of
the one להשם, the blood is in the vessel, maybe חבירו מזווג
לו, chaveiro mezaveg lo, you can bring a mate and pair it
to it if the לעזאזל L'Azazel. died. So in that case you
know that the one you're bringing is לעזאזל. L'Azazel So the גמרא
Gemara says, no, that's not necessarily what he's saying. נהי דשמעת ליה
לחנניה דלא הוי דחוי, Nehi d'shamat lei l'Chananya d'lo havei dachui, it's
true that from חנניה המצרי you understand that the blood that's in
the vessel is not pushed away, remains valid. דלא בעיא הגרלה מי
שמעת ליה, D'lo ba'ya hagrala mi shamat lei, you never heard from
him you don't have to do a lottery. דילמא מייתי ומגריל, Dilma
mayti u'magril, maybe you bring two goats and you do a lottery.
So what do you do? You have the blood in the כוס
kos from the one, in the vessel from the one that was
slaughtered. Now you need to replace the שעיר לעזאזל. Se'ir L'Azazel. You
can't just take one and say, ah, this is שעיר לעזאזל. Se'ir
L'Azazel. What you have to do is you have to take two,
go through the lottery procedure again. The one that's לעזאזל L'Azazel. is
now לעזאזל. L'Azazel The one that's להשם is the one you can't
use because you already have the blood here. So the one that's
להשם you set aside, you wait till it has a blemish, you
redeem it. So it's true he says you don't have to throw
out the blood, you can still use the blood. But it doesn't
mean you could arbitrarily pick one and say, this is לעזאזל. L'Azazel.
You might have to go through the lottery procedure again. And since
you have to go through the lottery procedure, we're back to square
one where even the one לעזאזל L'Azazel. has to be fit to
be להשם because you don't know which is which. So the גמרא
Gemara says, אלא אמר רב יוסף הא מני רבי שמעון היא. Ela
amar Rav Yosef ha meni Rabbi Shimon hi. Okay, there's another opinion
which clearly has a scenario like this that you don't have to
do a lottery. דתניא, D'tanya, we taught in a ברייתא, Braisa, רבי
שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, we taught in a ברייתא, Braisa, מת אחד מהן
מביא חבירו בלא הגרלה דברי רבי שמעון. Met echad mehen mevi chaveiro
belo hagrala divrei Rabbi Shimon. Very simple. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says
explicitly, if one of them died, right, whether the other one has
been slaughtered, hasn't, whatever, you don't have to go through the lottery
procedure again, just designate a substitute. So we have a clear position
of רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon that there are times where you'll directly
designate לעזאזל. L'Azazel, And in that case, you might have thought that
without a blemish it's either מותר mutar or at least you don't
transgress. And therefore the extra להשם is telling me that no, the
one that's לעזאזל L'Azazel. even if it's directly designated has to be
unblemished and you transgress if it is blemished. Okay. אמר רבא, Amar
Rava, רבא Rava says, לא נצרכה. lo nitzrecha. Here's another scenario without
getting into those opinions. כגון שהומם בו ביום. Kegon shehumam bo bayom.
Let's say I set... I did the lottery, okay, and now there's
the one that's לעזאזל. L'Azazel, And and what hap... I'm sorry, right,
there's the one that's לעזאזל. la-Azazel And now it got a blemish.
Okay, so it got a blemish, I don't want to use it,
which is interesting because רבא Rava sort of assumes that I already
know you can't use it with a blemish, which seems to have
been part of what the פסוק pasuk was teaching us. Okay, but
anyway, it's got a blemish and I can't use it. So in
this case, everybody would agree I don't have to do another lottery.
What I want to do is I want to transfer the קדושה
kedusha away from the one לעזאזל, la-Azazel. put that קדושה kedusha on
let's say some money, transfer it away, then take that קדושה kedusha
and reassign it to a new one. Okay, so this is a
case where you can designate a substitute, but everybody would agree you
don't need a lottery. Why not? Because you're not really... because what
you're really doing is you're directly designating a replacement. You're removing the
קדושה kedusha from one and you're putting it on its substitute. Okay,
you're not directly exchanging, that would be the איסור issur of תמורה.
Tmura. But in that case, everybody agrees you don't have to do
a lottery because it's derived from, it's not a brand new one,
it's derived from
the
first one
that
was
part of the lottery.
So
we're no
longer trying to answer how you can use a בעל מום, baal
mum, we're just trying to answer how you wouldn't need a lottery.
No, no, no, because then he's going to say, let's finish the
sentence. וחיללו על חבירו, V'chilalo al chaveiro, and you transferred the קדושה
kedusha to another goat with a מום. mum. The first one had
a מום mum and then you transferred it to another one. סלקא
דעתך אמינא, Salka daitach amina, בשלמא מעיקרא bishlama me'ikara לא ידעינן אי
האי נפקא לשם ואי האי נפקא לשם. lo yadeinan i hai nafka
l'shem v'i hai nafka l'shem. So I understand why it couldn't have
had a blemish to begin with. Why? Because because you had because
you didn't know whether it would wind up being the one להשם.
אבל הכא כיון דאיתפרש לשם לא לקי, Aval hacha keivan d'itparesh l'shem
lo laki,
here I would think that once the one להשם is designated, this
other one is clearly going to be לעזאזל. So I might think
you don't get lashes. What are you getting lashes for? When you
take the קדושה kedusha that's been transferred to this money from the
original goat and now transfer that קדושה kedusha to the substitute goat
לעזאזל, if that's... goat has a blemish, you transgress sanctifying an animal
with a blemish. So קמשמע לן kamashma lan that you do transgress.
So רבא Rava is really a variation of the previous one, it's
just a scenario where you don't need a lottery and therefore I
would have thought that you transgress that you somehow don't transgress when
the one לעזאזל has a blemish.
Obviously you transfer back to this first one then, are you transferring
it to money and then the
money is used to do what? No, because the first one has
a blemish. And so does the second one. I know, so you
have to transfer to one without a blemish. Okay, so anyway, but
again what's a little bit strange is whether the גמרא Gemara is
assuming that I would have known a blemish is no good or
not. Presumably until now it sounds like no, we didn't think a
blemish was intrinsically no good, it's just that we didn't know how
to choose whether it was going to be לה' la-Hashem or לעזאזל.
רבא Rava assumes that we knew a blemish was no good, which
raises the question then like, you know, again, why is this a
special case? All right, anyway now we move on. That's the question
about that it applies to the שעיר המשתלח. אמר מר, Amar mar,
three lines from the top, we are going to continue to focus
on sanctifying קרבנות korbanot with a blemish. משום רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה,
Mishum Rabbi Yose b'Rabbi Yehuda, אף קבלת הדם. af kabbalat hadam. Not
only is there a prohibition in sanctifying, slaughtering, burning an animal, sprinkling
the blood with a blemish and each one is a separate prohibition,
but there's even a prohibition of catching the blood, of receiving the
blood. Right, for those that remember זבחים, Zevachim, right, there are four
stages, right, שחיטה, shechita, קבלה, kabbala, הולכה, holacha, and זריקת הדם. zerikat
hadam. So שחטינג, shechting, catching the blood, sprinkling the blood, and moving,
bringing the blood to the altar. So bringing the blood is not
mentioned here, that anyway is always this עבודה avoda that is somewhat
that is somewhat secondary, it's a real עבודה avoda but in theory
you don't have to do it because you're standing right by the
altar. But he is now, but comes along רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה
Rabbi Yose b'Rabbi Yehuda and is insisting that at least the catching
of the blood, which is a key עבודה, avoda, also you transgress.
So מאי טעמא דרבי יוסי ברבי יהודה, mai ta'ama d'Rabbi Yose b'Rabbi
Yehuda, where does he get this from? Where in the verse do
you see that the catching of the blood of an animal with
a blemish is a part of the offering of such an animal
and you transgress? אמר קרא, Amar kra, the verse says, ומעוך וכתות
ונתוק וכרות לא תקריבו אלו לה'. u'ma'uach v'chatut v'natua'ch v'karut lo takrivu
elu la-Hashem. So it says all these different types of blemishes, crushed
and cut and whatever, a lot of these refer to the genitalia,
you shall not bring these to God. So there's another פסוק pasuk,
that says לא תקריבו. lo takrivu. If you remember yesterday we listed
a couple of times it says לא תקריבו, lo takrivu, you know,
what was the פסוק, pasuk כל אשר בו מום לא תקריבו, kol
asher bo mum lo takrivu, it says don't bring a lot of
times. So one of them was for sanctifying, one was for שחיטה,
shechting, then it says ועל המזבח לא תעלו לריח ניחוח v'al hamizbe'ach
lo ta'alu l'rei'ach nicho'ach which is for burning and for sprinkling the
blood. So we have another לא תקריבו. lo takrivu. This verse and
this verse therefore mean don't even catch the blood. זו קבלת הדם
שאמר רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה Zu kabbalat hadam she'amar Rabbi Yose b'Rabbi
Yehuda that he is saying. Again this phrase, this is the catching
that he is saying, that's a funny phrase, you know, it constantly
is reminding us that that's his position. We'll see that again. Anyway
the גמרא Gemara says like this, ולתנא קמא האי לא תקריבו למה
לי? u'l'tanna kamma hai lo takrivu lamma li? What does the תנא
קמא tanna kamma do with that verse? The תנא קמא tanna kamma
who says that the prohibition does not apply to catching of the
blood. So מיבעי ליה, mibba'ei lei, he needs it, לזריקת דמים, l'zerikat
damim, for the sprinkling of the blood. So the גמרא Gemara says
one minute, והא נפקא ליה מעל המזבח, v'ha nafka lei mei'al hamizbe'ach,
didn't we learn yesterday you get that from the verse on the
altar? And that and therefore you can't use this verse for that,
you don't need this verse for that. So the גמרא Gemara says
no, אורחא דקרא דמשתעי הכי. orcha dikra d'mishtaei hachi. When the verse
says לא תקריבו אלו לה', lo takrivu elu la-Hashem, it's not coming
to teach you a new prohibition, it's just, you know, that's the
way the פסוק Pasuk talks, which sort of sounds like a רבי
ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael approach, like דברה תורה כלשון בני אדם, dibra Torah
kilshon bnei adam, don't get so hung up on an extra phrase.
Now of course it's a little bizarre because right, first of all
that's all our דרשות, and yesterday we learned every separate act from
לא תקריבו, lo takrivu, לא תקריבו, lo takrivu, how here can we
say oh don't make a big deal out of לא תקריבו lo
takrivu the פסוק pasuk just says it sometimes? So the שיטה מקובצת
Shita Mekubetzet says that maybe it's because here it's talking about things
that are particularly like, you know, offensive or repugnant, you know, talking
about all of these like mutilated genitalia. So לא תקריבו אלו lo
takrivu elu is not just saying it's a prohibition, it's sort of
saying like this is inappropriate to bring this to God, this is
not the type of thing you should be bringing to God. So
that's what it means by אורחא דקרא דמשתעי הכי, orcha dikra d'mishtaei
hachi, that this verse is more sort of making a, as it
were, almost like, you know, a moral statement, not a lim, not
a negative prohibition. Even if that's true, it's still a little bit
funny. Normally the גמרא Gemara in such an explicit verse of don't
do this, the גמרא Gemara would normally interpret to mean that it's
coming to prohibit something. And the גמרא Gemara. is so persuaded by
this response that it feels it has to give up this פסוק
pasuk even according to רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה. Rabbi Yose b'Rabbi Yehuda.
So let's take a look. The גמרא Gemara says רבי יוסי ברבי
יהודה נמי אורחא דקרא דמשתעי הכי? Rabbi Yose b'Rabbi Yehuda nami orcha
dikra d'mishtaei hachi? אורחא דקרא הוא? Orcha dikra hu? Isn't that just
a way the תורה Torah talks and it's not really coming to
prohibit? So the גמרא Gemara, says אי הכי נמי, in hachi nami,
you're right. אלא קבלת הדם מנא ליה? Ella kabbalat hadam minalei? Where
do you know about catching the blood, that that's prohibited? נפקא ליה
מהא, Nafka lei mei'ha, from the following פסוק. pasuk ומיד בן נכר
לא תקריבו אלו לה'. U'miyad ben nechar lo takrivu elu la-Hashem.
Okay, the פסוק pasuk. says you cannot, not only can you not
accept animals with a blemish, you can't bring them, you also can't
accept them from non-Jews, which by the way is quite fascinating as
תוספות Tosafot points out, this פסוק pasuk. is pretty clear that you
could normally accept קרבנות korbanot from non-Jews, right, so the whole דרשה
drasha. we discussed yesterday in Okay, the פסוק pasuk *pasuk* says you
cannot, not only can you not accept animals with a blemish, you
can't bring them, you also can't accept them from non-Jews. Which, by
the way, is quite fascinating as תוספות Tosafot *Tosafos* points out, this
פסוק pasuk, *pasuk* is pretty clear that you could accept normal קרבנות
korbanot, *korbanos* from non-Jews, right? So the whole דרשה drasha *drasha* we
discussed yesterday, a non-Jew brings a קרבן korban *korban*, learned out from
איש איש *ish ish*, it's pretty clear from this פסוק pasuk, *pasuk*
that a non-Jew can bring a קרבן korban *korban*. It just says
don't bring them with a blemish. Okay, so, but so he says,
why does it have to add that verse?
Maybe that's implicit. If you can't bring it, a non-Jew can't bring
it. So the reason it says לא תקריבו lo takrivu? *lo takrivu*
is זו היא קבלת הדם kabalat hadam? *zu hi kabalas hadam* שאמר
רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה Rabbi Yose b'Rabbi Yehuda *she'amar Rebbi Yossi b'Rebbi
Yehuda*. That's where he learns out the idea of even the catching
of the blood. Right, except this is a לא תקריבו lo takrivu,
*lo takrivu* where the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* doesn't say אורחא דקרא orcha
dekra. *orcha d'kra*. Again, the way the שיטה מקובצת Shita Mekubetzet *Shita
Mekubetzet* explains אורחא דקרא orcha dekra, *orcha d'kra*, you can't say anytime
the פסוק pasuk *pasuk* says it, it's not serious. גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s
always learning it out from extra don't don't don't. I mean, my
God, it's more explicit than an extra ה *hey* or ו *vav*.
So he just says it's no, it's because it's in the context
of all this mutilated genitalia that the פסוק pasuk *pasuk* is really
saying like הקריבהו נא לפחתך *hakrivehu na l'pachatecha*. This is not the
type of thing you want to be bringing.
This one isn't by
the way, this is just yes, straight, a straight prohibition, don't bring
it even from a non-Jew. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, לתנא
קמא האי לא תקריבו lo takrivu. למה לי *l'Tanna Kamma hai lo
takrivu lama li*? Why do you, what do you do with this
extra פסוק Pasuk *pasuk*? So he says for the פשט pshat *pshat*,
מיבעי ליה להאי *mibaye lei l'hai* for the following reason. סלקא דעתך
אמינא *salka da'atach amina*, I would have thought, הואיל ולא V'lo, נצטוו
בני נח על מחוסרי אברים *ho'il v'lo nitztavevu Bnei Noach al mechusrei
evarim*, he maybe, here's why I would have thought that maybe you
could have accepted such a sacrifice from a non-Jew. Because the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says elsewhere that if a non-Jew wants to follow the
תורה Torah *Torah* law and bring a sacrifice on his own altar,
right, non-Jews are not prohibited to bring on their במות *bamas*, on
their private altars. So he wants to bring on his own altar
a sacrifice to God and he wants to follow תורה Torah *Torah*
law about, I mean not that it applies to a Jew, but
what's is there a הלכה *halacha* that applies to non-Jews? So believe
it or not, there is a הלכה *halacha* that applies, we normally
know about שבע מצוות בני נח sheva mitzvot bnei Noach. *Sheva Mitzvos
Bnei Noach* that are the הלכה *halacha* that applies to non-Jews. The
גמרא *Gemara* understands that there's actually הלכות *halachos* about how בני נח
*Bnei Noach* bring sacrifices if they want to do it according to,
according to what הלכה *halacha* dictates for non-Jews. And that הלכה *halacha*
is, yes, and that הלכה *halacha* is is that they cannot bring
animals that are missing a limb, but they do not have the
limitation of of them having to be completely unblemished. There's more latitude.
So I might have thought that since the תורה Torah *Torah* allows
them to bring sacrifices that are blemished as long as they're not
lacking a limb on their own altar, in their own temple if
they're bringing it to God, maybe they could bring by the same
standards in our temple. So סלקא דעתך אמינא הואיל ולא נצטוו בני
נח אלא מחוסרי אברים *salka da'atach amina ho'il v'lo nitztavevu Bnei Noach
ela mechusrei evarim*, since they were only commanded, prohibited against bringing animals
lacking a limb, so I might have thought לא שנא במזבח דידו
ולא שנא במזבח דידן *lo shena b'mizbeach didu v'lo shena b'mizbeach didan*,
not only can they bring it on their altars, they can even
bring it in our temple that way. קא משמע לן kamashma lan,
*ka mashma lan*, not that way, that when you're bringing it in
our temple you have to operate by our standards and we only
bring קרבנות *korbanos* in our temple regardless of who the one is
bringing it if they are unblemished. Okay, although that when you bring
out of your temple, you have sort of like a greater amount
of latitude. So in my mind actually this
interesting re-parallel, sort of the development that occurs, like in the 16th
century and beyond about questions about definitions of עבודה זרה avodah zarah,
*avoda zara* and those who sort of say, well, עבודה זרה *avoda
zara* is defined differently for Jews and for non-Jews. For non-Jews there's
more latitude about what type of belief system and worship is defined
as עבודה זרה *avoda zara*. There are things that are considered acceptable,
whatever,
non-יהודי *non-Yehudi*, Jews have like a different standard. So here it's like,
if you want to bring a sacrifice in your in your temple
to God, there's more latitude. In our temple,
we have, we're more limits, limiting standards and therefore that's what the
פסוק *pasuk* is needed. So you cannot have just assumed if it's
not good for Jews, it's not good for non-Jews. And therefore the
פסוק *pasuk* is coming to tell you פשט pshat *pshat* that from
non-Jews it's also not good, but not this new idea that even
catching the blood is part of it.
But in their in their temple, they don't have to restrict themselves
to the same קרבנות *korbanos* that we do in terms of type,
do they?
Can they do a pig? Well, the גמרא *Gemara* does imagine, does
have discussions about like imagine different types of things, עולה olah. *olah*,
שלמים *shelamim* and so on for non-Jews, but again it's an interesting
question. I'm trying to remember the סוגיא sugya *sugya* that probably also
is in the context of bringing them as a קרבן Korban *korban*
in the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash *Beis HaMikdash* whether, you know, you
accept the full range of קרבנות *korbanos* from non-Jews. I don't know
if there's, you're probably right that there's no discussion of
how what types of קרבנות *korbanos* are defined. A, like do they
have the same definitions in terms of gender and year of the
animal? And number two, do they right, can they even invent some
new type?
Right, they want to bring a camel.
Whatever it is. Oh, oh, that's what you meant. I thought you
meant can I have a concept of a קרבן Korban *korban* in
which I eat half and the כהן Kohen *kohen* eats half, or
they certainly, do they even need a concept of a כהן Kohen.
*kohen*? I mean there's even a question, on a במה *bama* we
don't need a concept of a כהן Kohen. *kohen*. So that's an
interesting question which I don't know the answer.
No, because then you're saying if if that would be the case
then we couldn't seriously entertain a הוה אמינא *hava amina* that we
can put a pig on a מזבח mizbeach. *mizbeach* because it would
be okay for Meir.
Yeah, okay, but at least within the genre that we do accept,
I mean it was some type of a הוה אמינא *hava amina*.
You do understand, I mean look, according to this explanation it's just
reading the פסוק *pasuk* like a פשוטה *pshuta* and it's right, פשט
*pshat* of the פסוק *pasuk*. implies that I might have thought to
accept it from a non-Jew. You don't bring it, but maybe you
can accept it from a non-Jew? No, don't bring it from a
non-Jew either.
You were just telling us the second before how disgusting that was
to be bringing some, you know, maimed קרבן, Korban but it's okay
from... that's only for Jews? I'm all worked up.
I understand, I'm just telling you the פשט of the פסוק, right?
פשט of the פסוק is it was a הוה אמינא you could
accept it from non-Jews and it says no, don't. Yes, what's the
context of to whom the non-Jew is sacrificing?
Are they saying
it's only if they
sacrifice to our God on their own personal...
Yes, because otherwise it's עבודה זרה, and that's one of the top
of the שבע מצוות בני נח. Now how exactly you define another
God, right, if they, you know, believe in a transcendent God but
they have a completely different story about that God, is that, you
know, you know, so the generally the assumption is is that the
story that you tell about God is not the definitional about what
it means to worship God. It's more about the question of like,
you know, a transcendence God, a single God, and so on. Those
are the more sort of central aspects.
I was going to say it also says something about the elemental
קדושה kedusha of the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash because the animals are
okay to bring to God outside of the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash
but inside we don't want to put the same... so it's something
about the actual space of the מזבח.
Mizbeiach, Right, that's an interesting point. You're right, meaning is it about
the space or is it somehow that it's sort of like it's
our show, it's our standards? But you're probably right, it probably has
much more to do with that sense of what is appropriate at
a place in this space, right. All right, so now the גמרא
says לשנא אחרינא, lishna achrina, which I discussed yesterday and even made
a little blog post yesterday about this, about these parallel versions which
seem to be sourced, you know, have a slightly different language and
seem to be sourced, as רש״י Rashi pointed out, have a more
of an ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael Aramaic language to them, so seem
to have a different source. Anyway, לשנא אחרינא, lishna achrina, so another
version of this. רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה אומר, Rabbi Yose b'Rabbi Yehuda
omer, אף אקבלת הדם. af akabalat hadam.
You transgress even by catching the blood of this animal with a
blemish. מאי טעמא? mai ta'ama? דכתיב ומעוך וכתות dechtiv ume'uach vechatut etc.
לא תקריבו אלה. lo takrivu eleh. אלה לא תקריבו, eleh lo takrivu,
זו קבלת הדם. zu kabalat hadam. וזריקה, vezrika, נפקא ליה מעל המזבח,
nafka lei me'al hamizbeach, from on the altar where the Rabbis learned
it out from. ורבנן נמי תיפוק ליה זריקה מעל המזבח, verabbanan nami
teipuk lei zrika me'al hamizbeach,
so the Rabbis presumably they should learn out sprinkling the blood from
על המזבח al hamizbeach and you're back to the question what do
they do with the verse of לא תקריבו? lo takrivu הכי נמי,
hachi nami, you're right, they do. אלא לא תקריבו דמעוך למאי אתא?
ela lo takrivu deme'uach lemai ata? So now we don't give that
weird answer you gotta admit that we gave a minute ago which
was אורחא דקרא. Okay, if it says לא תקריבו, it sounds like
it's prohibiting something new. רבי Rebbi יוסי ברבי יהודה says it's prohibiting
catching the blood, so what do the רבנן Rabbanan say it's prohibiting?
למאי אתא? lemai ata? מפקינן לבמת יחיד, mafkinan lebamat yachid,
that you can't even bring an animal with a blemish on your
private altar, which is interesting. We just spoke about the non-Jew, now
it's speaking, you know, like a different somebody who's, you know, from
outside the community but bringing in the same space. Now we're talking
about a Jew but bringing on an at an a different space,
an altar. So even on an altar a Jew cannot bring with
a blemish, and that's what the extra לא תקריבו. That this prohibition
applies even on a private altar, not even in the בית המקדש
Beis HaMikdash. at a period when private altars were allowed. לרבי יוסי
ברבי יהודה האי מיבעי ליה לבמת יחיד, leRabbi Yose b'Rabbi Yehuda hai
mibayei lei lebamat yachid, doesn't he need it for that? אין הכי
נמי, in hachi nami, you're right, he does. אלא תקריבה דקבלה מנא
ליה, ela takriva dekabala minalei, where does he know that you can't
do it even for קבלת הדם? מיד בני נכר לא תקריבו זו
קבלת הדם. miyad benei nechar lo takrivu zu kabalat hadam. Back to
where we started from, that it says don't accept from the non-Jew,
he feels that that's a superfluous verse that's taken for granted, so
that's coming to say even the catching of the blood you transgress.
Which means catching the blood on a Jewish altar.
On a Jewish, yes, even
though it's written by the
non-Jew, but it's extra because it would have been obvious. רבנן איצטריך,
Rabbanan itztarich, no, you need it by a non-Jew. סלקא דעתך אמינא
בני נח אין מצווין אלא מחוסר איבר בבמה דילהון, salta da'atach amina
bnei Noach ein metzuvin ela mechusar eivar bebama dilaon, since Noahides are
only prohibited when it's lacking a limb when they're bringing it on
their altar, תימא אנן נמי נקבל מינהון, teima anan nami nekabel minehon,
maybe we can accept from them, קא משמע לן, תותי דזה מכל
אלה דלא מקבלינן. toti d'zeh mikol eleh delo mekabelinan. No,
you don't accept even, you know, if blemished animals even from non-Jews,
and that's what it's teaching you. So in the end it's the
same debate. Do you assume the verse of non-Jews is superfluous and
teaching you catching of the blood, or do you assume it's necessary,
maybe there would have been more, you know, a different a different
standard and it's telling you when it's in the temple you actually
cannot. Actually it raises an interesting question going back to Seth's point,
since we're also learned the one new thing we introduced here was
the idea that rather than saying oh אורחא דקרא, which was very
strange, it's actually saying that the לא תקריבו from מעוך וכתות me'uach
vechatut is telling us a new thing, that even on a private
altar when those were permitted, you cannot bring with a blemish. So
here's an interesting question. A non-Jew comes to me on my private
altar and asks me if I will bring for him a קרבן
Korban. with a blemish. With, right? So if Seth is right, it's
only because it's the space, the temple, but if it's the alternative,
you know, if the alternative is no, when it's sort of a
Jewish, it's not the temple per se, it's like when it's a
Jewish show, we go by Jewish... so if he's asking me to
bring his קרבן Korban on my
altar, so maybe there too a blemish would be prohibited. So that's
a nice נפקא מינא nafka mina between Seth's approach and my approach.
Okay? But now we see that it's prohibited for non-Jews on, you
know, at least in the temple and it's prohibited even on a
private altar. I don't know, I have to explore that. It's a
good question, just occurred to me now. I'll have to explore. Okay.
So now we've got, okay, מתקיף לה ריש לקיש. matkif lah Reish
Lakish. Okay, now, so now we've laid out that you have all
of these prohibitions of sanctifying and bringing an animal with a blemish
and we've extended it to private altars, we've extended it to non-Jews
and so on. Now ריש לקיש Reish Lakish is going to question
this whole approach, or you know, some fundamental aspect here. שמא לא
שנינו, shema lo shaninu, maybe this whole thing only applies אלא בתם
שנעשה בעל מום. ella b'tam shenasa baal mum. If it started off
unblemished and then it became blemished.
דעובר, d'over, it should be that you transgress. דאי בעל מום מעיקרא,
d'ee baal mum me'ikara, if it's something that was originally a בעל
מום, baal mum דקלא בעלמא הוא, dikla b'alma hu, it's like a
palm tree, you know, it's not even an animal. Why are we
having, how is it different than if I went ahead and I
sanctified my car? Now, because let's say, now of course the difference
is if I sanctify my car, I'm doing it to the temple
treasury. But let's say I went and I said something absurd, I
took my car and I said, I am sanctifying my car as
an עולה. olah. So would I transgress? No, what we would say
is the translation of those words means that it, that the money,
the proceeds should be used to bring an עולה. olah, Okay, but
it wouldn't be like I did something wrong. I mean, you know,
it's just sanctifying something that's not, can't be used for that and
we'll use the proceeds for that. So let's say the same with
an animal with a blemish. Now, that makes a lot of sense.
The question is, you're only over on trying to מקדיש maktish something
with a בעל מום Baal Mum? then, if it's, so the
only way you'd be over is if it started unblemished. Now the
question is, who cares that it started unblemished? Who cares if it
was born unblemished? If by the time, right, he says, oh, so
maybe the only prohibition is when it started unblemished. But who cares?
Let's say it was born unblemished, but the time I get around
to sanctifying it, it's got the blemish. So again, how's it any
different than my car? How's it any different than a palm tree?
Right now this thing is completely unfit. So why is it different?
So רש"י Rashi says, look, technically you're right, it has a blemish
before you sanctify it, who cares if it had it from birth
or had it later? But at least רש"י Rashi says sort of
psychologically,
it's, you know, you consider it to be more relevant. And you
consider it to be more in the, as a potential candidate for
קרבן korban, because it started without a blemish. And therefore, or you
might say even not just psychologically, you might say some objective standard,
it didn't start its life, it wasn't defined as being irrelevant. It
was something that was once defined as relevant and now became irrelevant.
So therefore maybe it's worse to sanctify that type of a thing
where it's really seen as like perverting the קדושה kedusha as opposed
to when the thing was always irrelevant and out of the category
where it's not perverting the קדושה, kedusha, it's just like, you know,
it's like sanctifying your car. You know, which it's directly interpreted to
mean the proceeds are going to go for that and it's not
seen as a perversion of, it's like, it's not like a missed
potential. You know, it's always like such a shame when somebody has
all of this potential and then they waste it, right? You know,
it's, you see a young person and they have all this amazing
potential and they waste it as opposed to somebody who never had
the potential. So רש"י's Rashi saying it was born without a blemish,
it had the potential and you sanctified and therefore you could see
that it's like wasted and perverted as opposed to something that was
always that way. Now that's the way רש"י Rashi feels. תוספות Tosafot
is bothered. תוספות Tosafot says look, if by the time you get
to sanctify it, it has a blemish, who really cares whether it
got that blemish earlier in its life or later in its life?
And תוספות Tosafot says that not what ריש לקיש Reish Lakish is
talking about. He's not talking about the prohibition of sanctifying. He's talking
about the prohibition of offering an animal with a blemish. Now you
might remember that we actually had a משנה mishna in בכורות Bechorot
that spoke about the different level of sanctity. If I sanctify an
unblemished animal and it gets a blemish, or I sanctify a blemished
animal. If I sanctify an unblemished animal, the sanctity begins as fit
for the altar. And therefore even after it gets a blemish, it
still has קדושת מזבח, kedushat mizbe'ach, it just can't be brought now.
As opposed to something that started with a blemish that I sanctified,
it never had קדושת מזבח, kedushat mizbe'ach, it was when the sanctity
hit, it wasn't fit. So תוספות Tosafot says like this: not the
prohibition of sanctifying, the prohibition of offering a קרבן, korban, maybe I
only transgress if I offered a קרבן korban. that had the, that
had the קרבן korban, sanctity and then got the blemish. Because that
actually has, that's a real קרבן korban that now can't be brought.
But if the animal was sanctified when it already had the blemish,
so then it never had the sanctity of a קרבן korban. and
therefore it's not like bringing a קרבן korban with a blemish because
it never even had the sanctity.
And what is it like then?
It's like what? It's like bringing חולין לעזרה, chullin l'azarah, right? It's
like, it's like if I sanctified my palm tree and I brought
it into the temple and I broke it in half. Okay, so
it's a weird stuff that I'm doing, but it's not the, it's
not the offering of a sacrifice with a blemish because it's never
had the קדושה kedusha of a sacrifice. And I'm bound by both
of them. All right, so those are the two interpretations. You know,
תוספות Tosafot really is a practical difference that It's a different level
of קדושה Kedusha and he focuses on the prohibition of offering. רש''י
Rashi says we're focusing on the act of sanctifying, it's more a-
so it's a psychological difference, a sort of a- a way I,
you know, a way I relate to it differently when it- whether
it was born or not, but halachically there's really no difference.
So for a second I was saying how disgusting it all was,
and I was saying, oh, it's only so- it's not so bad
if it didn't start-
no, no, no,
but we're saying we cannot fault you for bringing a קרבן korban,
with a blemish. I don't understand. Let's say I go ahead and
I take a, you know, a pig, right, into the בית המקדש
Beis HaMikdash and I slaughter it. So I've obviously done something which
is sacrilege and disgusting, but I didn't bring a קרבן korban, with
a blemish, okay? In the technical sense, right, it is not a
קרבן korban, with a blemish. So that's what תוספות Tosafot says. If
you sanctified it after the blemish, it never is defined as a
קרבן. korban So how can we technically make you transgress for a
קרבן korban with a blemish? That's the way תוספות Tosafot understands the
question. Okay, so but for רש''י Rashi the question is about the
act of sanctifying. Let's take a look. So, okay, עכשיו. Achshav. So
אמר ליה רבי חייא בר רב יוסף. Amar Lei Rabbi Chiya Bar
Rav Yosef. So רבי חייא בר רב יוסף Rabbi Chiya Bar Rav
Yosef says it's implicit in the verse. It says שרוע וקלוט Sarua
VeKalut in the list of things you can't bring, from where we
learn you can't sanctify, you can't offer, it includes שרוע וקלוט, Sarua
VeKalut, כתיב בפרשה. Ketiv BeParsha. והני בעלי מומין מעיקרא נינהו. VeHani Baalei
Mumin MeIkara Ninhu. Those are birth defects from birth. What are they?
שרוע Sarua is that the limbs are disproportionate and קלוט Kalut is
that the hooves are- are fused, are not closed, are not split.
So he says, look, within this list, and that's how we learn
you can't sanctify, you can't bring, it includes things that were always
had- that were always had a blemish. So you cannot say that
it only applies when it was born without a blemish. והני בעלי
מומין. VeHani Baalei Mumin. אמר ליה. Amar Lei. So he said back
to him, שמא לא שנינו אלא בתמורה. Shema Lo Shaninu Ela BiTmura.
Fine. Okay, you've proved the point of starting with a blemish, that
it applies there. But now I have another way I want to
limit it. Maybe it only applies to a תמורה. Tmura Why? And
here we see its relationship to the whole discussion of תמורה. Tmura.
דתנן. DeTnan. חומר בתמורה מבזבח. Chomer BiTmura MiBeZevach. That the difference between
a תמורה Tmura. and a normal animal that's sanctified as a sacrifice,
שכן קדושה חלה עליה על בעל מום קבוע, SheKen Kedusha Chala Aleha
Al Baal Mum Kavuah,
because sanctity, full sanctity applies to a תמורה. Tmura Meaning what? Meaning
that again, I just told you that if I take an animal
that already has a blemish and I sanctify it, it never gets
קדושת מזבח Kedushat Mizbeach because, you know, the sanctity when it hit,
it wasn't fit for the altar at that initial moment. The one
exception to this is תמורה. Tmura Because the תורה Torah tells me
that the power of doing תמורה Tmura. is that the second animal
becomes sanctified like the first, even if the second animal has a
blemish. When we learn it from the verse that says that רע
בטוב או טוב ברע, Ra BeTov O Tov BeRa, that רע Ra
means with a blemish. That even if the second animal has a
blemish, the power of תמורה Tmura, is the קדושה Kedusha from the
first one is instilled in the second one even if the second
one has a blemish and it becomes קדושת מזבח Kedushat Mizbeach even
if the second one started with a blemish. So אביי Abaye says
like this. אביי Abaye says look- I'm sorry, ריש לקיש. Resh Lakish.
Fine, you've proven to me even if it starts with a blemish.
But I still don't like it. I still want to limit the
prohibition, whether according to תוספות Tosafos, of offering or whether according to
רש''י Rashi of sanctifying, to a type of case where the קדושה
Kedusha is real קדושת מזבח. Kedushat Mizbeach. And that doesn't apply if
it started with a blemish. So if you're going to prove to
me from the verse that it started with a blemish, I'm going
to read the verse as talking only about a תמורה. Tmura Because
in the case of a תמורה, Tmura then- then it can get
instilled with the קדושה Kedusha of a sacrifice even though it starts
with a blemish. And I still want to limit it to that
case of real קדושה Kedusha of a sacrifice.
Okay, yeah, this is the only case, but what about the בכורות?
Bechorot? What about the- oh, good point.
בכור Bechor with a blemish too. Right, that's a very good point.
Touché. Okay, so you're right because there it also happens automatically. Right,
okay, that's a very good point. Thank you.
Okay, so
אמר ליה רבי יוחנן. Amar Lei Rabbi Yochanan. So רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan says, לא שמיע לך הא דאמר רבי ינאי. Lo Shemia Lach
Ha DeAmar Rabbi Yannai. So רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
says, have you not heard what רבי ינאי Rabbi Yannai said, which
he said בחבורה? BeChavura? נמנו וגמרו. Nimnu VeGamru. In the sort of
convocation, you know, in some type of a gathering of the rabbis,
they took a vote, נמנו וגמרו, Nimnu VeGamru, and they concluded, meaning
that they really investigated the matter and came to the conclusion, המקדיש
בעל מום לגבי מזבח. HaMakdish Baal Mum Legabei Mizbeach. If you sanctify
an animal with a blemish and then you bring it, עובר משום
חמשה שמות. Over Mishum Chamisha Shemot. You transgress five, right? And the
five were sanctifying, slaughtering, sprinkling the blood, burning part of it, burning
all of it. We said that yesterday. But according to you, the
whole thing only applies by a תמורה Tmura. if it starts with
a blemish, right? And a תמורה Tmura, means you've transgressed yet again.
You've transgressed for doing the act of sanctifying, of doing a תמורה.
Tmura. ואי בתמורה נמי איכא שיתא. VeEi BiTmura Nami Ika Shita. And
if it's limited to a case of
תמורה, Temurah and it's
six, איכא נמי לאו דתמורה. Ika Nami Lav DeTmura. You have the
prohibition of a תמורה. tmura Okay, so basically based on the פסוק
and based on the idea that we said five, we've proven that
it applies to an animal that even starts with a blemish, even
though the sanctity you're instilling in it is not real קדושת מזבח.
Kedushat Mizbeach. not sanctified is not קדושת מזבח, Kedushas Mizbeiach, because when
it starts with a blemish it's not. So therefore, you know ריש
לקיש'ס Reish Lakish's logical question is good: how bad was it that
you sanctified it since you didn't give it קדושת מזבח? Kedushas Mizbeiach?
And number two is, how bad is it that you offer it
since you're not offering an animal that has קדושת קרבן? Kedushas Korban?
So why is the whole thing included in the prohibition of בעל
מום? baal mum So the גמרא says like this, let's treat it
just like I brought my palm tree into the בית המקדש Beit
HaMikdash, that I had sanctified. So the גמרא says אלא מאי, ela
mai, דבעל מום מעיקרא. debaal mum meikara. So you've proven to me
we're talking about an animal with a blemish and that the sanctity
is not special, it's not תמורה tmura based, it's sanctity that is
not למזבח. leMizbeiach. So right, so right. So you've proven your point,
but I'm still not satisfied about my conceptual question. So אמאי לקי,
amai laki, why are you getting lashes? דקלא בעלמא הוא, dikla bealma
hu, it's like a palm tree. So אמר ליה, amar lei, he
said דקלא לאו זילא מילתא, dikla lav zila milsa, מין עצים הוא,
min eitzim hu, a palm tree is not sort of is not
degrading, you know,
it's it's just wood. So the fact that you sanctified it is
not like you've perverted some
קדושה. Kedusha. בעל מום מעיקרא, Baal mum meikara, if something has a
blemish, although it's true the sanctity never became sanctity for the מזבח,
but nevertheless זילא מילתא, zila milsa, it's still some it's a sense
of some you know there's something
degrading about this. וכיון דחזי לתמי ואקדשיה למומי מחייב, vekeivan dechazi letami
veakdeshei lemumi mechayev,
because once you are dealing with an animal, the the possibility of
having brought a right animal is sort of right there in the
context. Right, if I take my car and I say I'm sanctifying
it as an עולה, olah. so it's a car, of course it's
not like oh you could have sanctified a sheep as an עולה.
olah. Basically what my words mean are, how they're interpreted is, you
take the proceeds and you use them for an עולה. olah, But
if I go ahead and I take an animal with a blemish
and I sanctify it, you said idiot, if you were trying to
sanctify this sheep as an עולה, olah you should have taken a
sheep that was unblemished. And the fact that you did it with
a sheep with a blemish is a perversion of the קדושה Kedusha
and therefore that's
not seen as something
categorically different, but it's just seen as a perversion and what I
could have done right is right there in the offing and it's
sort of being a missed opportunity. And similarly when I bring it
as a sacrifice you would have to say, according to תוספות, Tosafos
although technically this doesn't have the קדושה Kedusha of a sacrifice, but
it still is an animal that was sanctified for the sake of
an עולה olah and is being brought as an עולה olah, and
it has a blemish. So although in the technical הלכתית halachic sense,
the legal sense, the קדושה Kedusha was never קדושת קרבן Kedushas Korban
because it couldn't have been because it started with a blemish, but
nevertheless זילא מילתא, zila milsa, it's still a sense of having, you
know, perverted, having
having sort of missed this opportunity is very blatant and therefore you
transgress.
It's like a מראית עין maris ayin thing too?
Yes, so that's I think what sort of ריש לקיש Reish Lakish
is struggling with, is that ריש לקיש Reish Lakish for once, you
know, the גמרא is, you know, ריש לקיש Reish Lakish is being
very legalistic. And he's saying technically it's not a קרבן, korban. so
I don't understand how this is any different than taking my sanctified
palm tree into the altar in a technical legal sense. It's no
different. And the answer is, here actually the prohibition is not because
we technically categorize it as a קרבן, korban, but it's more as
you say, I don't say מראית עין maris ayin what other people
think, but it's more sort of at the at the experiential level,
at the sort of religious implications of the act, but not at
the technical legal definition of the act. Technically legally, you're right, a
sanctified sheep with a blemish, if it had the blemish to begin
with, is no different than a sanctified palm tree. So in the
legal sense, but it's sort of at the experiential sense, you know,
the religious implications of the act, they're different. But again, it's quite
I think it's again this fascinating clash of approaches because we so
much, you know, come from a גמרא approach where everything is its
legal definition, you know, but some things could legally be the same
and have very different sort of symbolic meaning, which is what the
response is. I'm sorry, what were you going to say?
Nobody's going to think that a palm tree can be brought as
a sacrifice. Right, of course it can't be, it can be... Alright,
maybe somebody... Alright, maybe somebody... Right, whatever. Maybe somebody's going to think
that you could bring an unblemished, a blemished animal.
Right, but he but זילא מילתא zila milsa is not about what
people think, זילא מילתא zila milsa is about the inappropriate nature of
that sort of in terms of like religious sensibilities. Possibly, possibly. Again,
one wonders presumably according to him let's say you sanctified a camel,
right, you know, and you brought it. So, you know, it's a,
you know, what would you say about that? Is it זילא מילתא?
zila milsa? I don't know.
Anyway, I had a hard problem
with ריש לקיש. Reish Lakish. Why? I mean it's...
You have a problem with ריש לקיש? Reish Lakish? I thought you
would like him because he's being a very legalistic approach.
No, it seems like what you were trying to establish, trying to
say before, it's getting through how like all discussing all these things...
Oh, because you think it's clear that the פסוק is about the
offensive nature of it and the legalistic should not be a problem.
That's a good point. But let's say you brought an animal that
you didn't sanctify at all with a blemish and you brought it
and you slaughtered it in the temple. Right, you wouldn't transgress. So
at some level it does have to be in the realm of
bringing of being a קרבן. korban. It's not just enough about the
offensive nature of the act. But now the גמרא takes an interesting
shift. So let's take a look. לשנא אחרינא, Lishna achrina, here's
again our לשנא אחרינא. Lishna achrina. אמר ליה Amar lei אפילו הכי
afilu hachi בזיא מילתא, bziya milta, even if that's true,
it's a, you know, it's... בזיא bziya is not exactly degrading like
a בזיון. bizayon. How would you translate בזיון? bizayon?
Embarrassment?
Not embarrassment. Unseemly?
Unseemly, somehow offensive, you know, it's disgusting. Anyway, right, it's a, you
know, it's
offensive. דדקלא במינא לא לקי. de-dakla b'mina lo laki. A palm tree
that there's no, that it's not like you could bring a different
type of a palm tree as a sacrifice. It's completely irrelevant. So
it's, you don't get lashes. It's not so offensive. לאפוקי בעל מום
כיון דאיכא במינא לקי. l'afukei ba'al mum keivan d'ika b'mina laki. By
an animal that's a blemish, although technically, as you point out, it
doesn't have the sanctity of a קרבן, korban, but nevertheless, you know,
since the alternative is obvious, there's something offensive about bringing this.
So what's the difference between the two לשנא אחרינאs? lishna achrina Nothing.
As I said yesterday and I said in my blog post,
לשנא אחרינאs lishna achrina in the, a לשנא אחרינא lishna achrina is
plural, they basically say exactly the same thing, just they have a
slightly different phrasing or come from it from a slightly different angle.
And the basic point is that we're two parallel, two parallel versions
of the סוגיא grew up and they were, and they were conflated
and both presented in this גמרא. Okay.
I'm sorry, I had a question as to why you need the
other one if the first one is, you know, obviously saying...
The editor of this, whether it was רבינא Ravina and רב אשי
Rav Ashi or whether it was
the סבוראים Savoraim or the גאונים, Geonim, decided that he wanted to
preserve both texts even if there really wasn't a substantive difference of
both texts.
Okay. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, so said רבא, Rava, השתא דאמרת טעמא
דבעל מום דלקי משום דבזיא מילתא היא. hashta d'amart ta'ama d'ba'al mum
d'laki mishum d'bziya milta hi. Now that you said the reason is
because of the sort of offensive nature of this...
For both versions of this?
Well, both of them said בזיא. bziya. One בזילא מילתא bzila milta
and בזיא מילתא. bziya milta. All right. Anyway, now that you said
that's the reason, and it's not just because technically it has קדושת
קרבן, kedushat korban, which it doesn't, it has קדושה kedusha but never
קדושה kedusha that would fit for קדושת קרבן. kedushat korban. So once
that's true, אפילו מקדיש ליה לדמי נסכים נמי לקי. afilu makdish lei
l'dmei nesachim nami laki. Even if you sanctify something, now this is
a jump because it's not as obvious at all. You take an
animal and you sanctify it not just as a, you know, not
just as a, what do you call it, not just as a,
as an עולה, olah, but you sanctify this animal with a blemish
and you say I'm going to take the proceeds and use it
to bring wine, to, you know, to bring נסכים. nesachim. You also
transgress. Why? Because somehow the use of an animal with a blemish
in the context of sanctifying things for, you know, for the within
the larger context of sanctifying things for, you know, sacrificial use is
considered to have been a wasted opportunity and offensive. Of course you
could say there's a huge difference. You know, if you were being
a more formalist then maybe you could say any temple sanctity, any
sacrificial sanctity of an animal with a blemish. But actually your intuition
would have been the opposite. If you're dealing more about sort of
the, you know, religious offensive nature of it, you would have said
when it's, when this could have been for exactly the purpose you
sanctified it for, an עולה, olah, and you used the wrong thing,
a blemished thing, that was offensive. If you're sanctifying it to use
the proceeds for something else, it's not so offensive. That really is
like sanctifying a car to use the proceeds. You're sanctifying a sheep
to use the proceeds for the oil offerings, so or the wine
offerings. So it's a little funny the way he makes the jump
because if anything the jump is, you know, the emphasis on the
offensive nature would have actually argued against applying it to this case,
which is less offensive. What's the big deal?
Of an animal with
a blemish.
Absolutely, right. So exactly that. So it's so funny he assumes that
because it's in the context of sacrificial use, using such an animal
and even though it's not the same type of thing that would
have been used for the thing you're sanctifying for. So again it's
quite strange. רש"י Rashi I think, somebody points out the problem about
this, about the fact that it's not exactly parallel. Let me just
see if it's רש"י. Rashi. Hold on.
Yeah, look at the last רש"י. Rashi. אפילו אקדשו לדמי נסכים דהשתא
ליכא בזיון כל כך. afilu akdesho l'dmei nesachim d'hashta leika bizayon kol
kach. It's not such a בזיון. bizayon. שאין במינו עולה לנסכים she'ein
b'mino olah l'nesachim because you don't bring sheep for, for wine offerings.
ועוד דהלו דמי אקדשו v'od d'halo d'mei akdesho and nevertheless you said
you only want to use the proceeds. אפילו הכי לקי. afilu hachi
laki. Nevertheless you get lashes. So it's okay to say that, it's
okay to make the claim that he believes that it extends to
that case, but it's not because we framed it as בזיון. bizayon.
Because we framed it as בזיון bizayon it would have been a
reason to say the opposite. Okay, but nevertheless that's his claim that
that is actually a problem. So let's take a look. So now
we are saying that it's not only a problem to sanctify it
for, directly for a sacrifice, but even for other types of proceeds
of sacrificial use. Okay, so let's take a look.
נמי לקי. nami laki. תני כוותיה דרבא, tani k'vatei d'Rava, we taught
like רבא. Rava.
נדבה תעשה אותו, nedava ta'aseh oto, this is the verse about, about
not bringing animals with a מום. mum. So the Torah says נדבה
תעשה אותו ולנדר. nedava ta'aseh oto u'l'neder. נדבה תעשה אתו ולנדר לא
ירצה. Nedava taaseh oso ule'Neder lo yiratzeh. You can make it a
נדבה, nedava, a gift, but not a vow. Now what does that
mean? Normally in חז"ל's Chazal understanding, the difference between נדר neder and
נדבה nedava is a נדר neder when I say הרי עלי, harei
alai, I take the obligation. נדבה nedava is when I say הרי
זו, harei zo, this is sanctified. But if the animal has a
blemish, the difference is not whether it's my obligation or you know
starts with me or starts with the animal, the difference is am
I bringing it as a קרבן korban. or am I doing some
other use for it. So they want to read the actual difference
in the verse of נדבה תעשה אתו ולנדר לא ירצה nedava taaseh
oso ule'neder lo yiratzeh meaning you can give it as a gift
to the temple but you can't use it as a קרבן. korban.
But that's not what in their you know terminology נדר neder and
נדבה nedava means. So they have to now reread the verse so
that נדר neder and נדבה nedava with their standard meaning of הרי
עלי harei alai and הרי זו harei zo fit in the פסוק
and their real line of the division is whether it's for a
קרבן korban, or whether it's for a gift to the בית המקדש.
So let's say we just said that if it's say קרבן, korban,
it's not קרבן, korban. an animal that's a בעל מום and I
want to use its proceeds for... yeah we're going to get to
נסכים, nesachim, then that's going to be a problem. If I want
to use its proceeds for בדק הבית bedek habayis then that's לכתחילה
lechatchila good.
Exactly. That's exactly what the פסוק is saying. If you want to
use this קרבן, korban. give it to בדק הבית. bedek habayis. So
נדבתה תעשה אתו, nedavatah taaseh oso, make it a נדבה nedava you
shall use it, זה קדשי בדק הבית. zeh kodshei bedek habayis. So
that means give it to the temple treasury. ואין לי אלא נדבה,
ve'ein li ela nedava, that's only if it's a נדבה nedava if
you say הרי זו, harei zo, you directly sanctify it. נדר מנין,
neder minayin, how do I know if I start with a הרי
עלי, harei alai, I can still when I come to sanctify it
I can still give it to בדק
הבית? bedek habayis? תלמוד לומר ולנדר. talmud lomar ule'neder. So talk about
a creative reread of the פסוק. נדבתה תעשה אתו ולנדר. nedavatah taaseh
oso ule'neder. You can make it a נדבה nedava or a נדר
neder as long as you give it to the בדק הבית. bedek
habayis.
לא ירצה. lo yiratzeh.
That's the other way to read the פסוק. Okay. יכול אפילו קדשי
מזבח, yachol afilu kodshei mizbeach,
maybe I can give this these things to the altar? תלמוד לומר
ולנדר לא ירצה. talmud lomar ule'neder lo yiratzeh. Don't give it as
a נדר. neder. Now here the emphasis is not on the word
נדר neder but לא ירצה. lo yiratzeh. ריצוי ritzuy means something that
is given and that and that is desirable by God, it's given
as an offering to God. So לא ירצה lo yiratzeh means don't
give it as a sacrifice. זה קדשי מזבח zeh kodshei mizbeach on
the word לא ירצה. lo yiratzeh. ואין לי אלא נדר, ve'ein li
ela neder, now that's only don't give it as a נדר, neder,
something starts with הרי עלי, harei alai, don't give it as a
sacrifice. נדבה מנין, nedava minayin, how do I know that I can't
if I'm trying to give it as a sacrifice I can't even
give it as a נדבה, nedava, הרי זו? harei zo? תלמוד לומר
נדבה. talmud lomar nedava. Okay so meaning the way the תורה Torah
reads it reads the verse as again it's a problem because the
תורה makes the division between נדר neder and נדבה. nedava. חז"ל Chazal
make the difference between whether it's for the altar or for the
בדק הבית. bedek habayis. So the way they read the verse is
נדבתה תעשה אתו ולנדר, nedavatah taaseh oso ule'neder, if you want to
just give it as a נדר neder or נדבה nedava to the
בית המקדש to the בדק הבית bedek habayis that's fine. However,
נדבתה תעשה אתו ולנדר לא ירצה, nedavatah taaseh oso ule'neder lo yiratzeh,
whether you're doing a נדבה nedava or נדר neder it can't לא
ירצה lo yiratzeh won't be accepted as a קרבן korban? as a
sacrifice. All right so that's a very you know that's because of
the terminology of נדר neder and נדבה nedava they have to read
the פסוק in a creative way. Anyway that's not our direct focus.
רבי אומר, Rebbi omer, here's where we're coming to discuss, לא ירצה
lo yiratzeh it shall not be accepted, ברצות גופו הכתוב מדבר. birtzos
gufo haksav medaber. That's talking that you cannot bring the thing itself
as a sacrifice. So what's he adding? היינו תנא קמא, hainu tanna
kamma, isn't that what we just said? מאי לאו בהא קמיפלגי, mai
lav beha kamiflegi, must be this is what they're debating. דתנא קמא
סבר אפילו אקדשיה לדמי נסכים נמי לקי. de'tanna kamma savar afilu akdishei
lidmei nesachim nami laki. The תנא קמא tanna kamma doesn't emphasize the
animal itself. So that means according to the תנא קמא tanna kamma
even if you were to sanctify it for its proceeds to be
used in a sacrificial context you would have transgressed. ורבי סבר ברצות
גופו לקי. ve'Rebbi savar birtzos gufo laki. No, only if you're trying
to use the animal itself you get lashes. אבל בדמי נסכים לא
לקי. aval bidmei nesachim lo laki. If you want to sanctify it
to use its proceeds then you do not get lashes. Okay. It's
still... no it's not so clear because תוספות actually points out there
are a number of גמרות Gemaras that talk about things like sanctifying
a female animal to use for an עולה, olah sanctifying things that
are not appropriate but your point is that you want to use
the proceeds for it. And according to the approach here of רבי
Rebbi or of the תנא קמא tanna kamma or who was it
of רבא Rava here who said it, whoever it was,
רבא Rava actually anytime you would sanctify an animal to use the
proceeds for the עולה olah. or even the proceeds for wine or
whatever that would be a you would transgress which is not what
we normally assume when we're learning קדשים. Kodashim. There's a lot of
discussion of sanctifying things for their proceeds including animals for their proceeds
that don't seem to be problematic. And that seems to be the
position of רבי Rebbi which is the more logical one. Only if
you're trying to use the thing itself. But if you're trying to
use the proceeds even in a sacrificial context that's not problematic. לכתחילה?
Lechatchila? Yeah presumably yeah. And what's strange is that רבא Rava assumes
that it's obvious because of the approach of ביזא דמילתא biza demilsa
but ביזא דמילתא biza demilsa actually much more supports רבי's Rabbi approach.
Okay anyways שמע מינה. shma mina. So you're right. So that is
the debate. That is the debate of רבי Rabbi and the תנא
קמא. tanna kamma. Now ואלא אותו למה לי? ve'ela oso lamah li?
What do you do with אותו? oso? Now ואלא ve'ela is a
funny phrase. It's not like it's not like responding to something before.
But רש"י Rashi says now that we have this דרשה נדבתה תעשה
אתו ולנדר nedavatah taaseh oso ule'neder we've learned that whole פסוק, אותו
oso is a... limiting word. So now that we're looking at the
פסוק, what is the import of the word אותו, Oto, it, as
opposed to something else? So the גמרא says לכדתניא, Lichdetanya, like we
taught in a ברייתא: braita: ונדבת תעשה אותו, V'nadavta Ta'aseh Oto, אותו
תעשה נדבה ואי אתה עושה תמימה נדבה לבית הבדק, Oto Ta'aseh Nedava
V'ee Ata Oseh Tmima Nedava L'veit Habedek, to tell you the reverse.
This, an animal with a blemish goes to בדק הבית, Bedek Habayit,
but the reverse is also prohibited. An unblemished animal you cannot sanctify
to the בדק הבית. Bedek Habayit. A blemished one only goes to
בדק הבית, Bedek Habayit, not to the temple, not to a sacrifice,
and an unblemished one only can be sanctified as a sacrifice, not
for בדק הבית. Bedek Habayit. It's also a perversion of its, you
know, of its appropriate use. So מכאן אמרו, Mikan Amru, from here
they said, המקדיש תמימים לבית הבדק עובר בעשה. Hamakdish Tmimum L'veit Habedek
Over B'aseh. If you sanctify an unblemished animal for the temple treasury,
you transgress a positive, a מצות עשה. mitzvot aseh. Well, we're going
to discuss that in a minute. You might not get מלקות malkut
anyway, it's a דיבור, dibbur, which is לאו שאין בו מעשה, lav
she'ein bo ma'aseh, but it's not a לאו תעשה. lo ta'aseh. Why?
Because it says ונדבת תעשה אותו. V'nadavta Ta'aseh Oto. What should be
for בדק הבית? Bedek Habayit? Something which is a blemish. So if
it's unblemished and it's בדק הבית, Bedek Habayit, you've transgressed that positive
מצוה. mitzvah. Now the ברייתא braita goes on, ומניין אף בלא תעשה?
Uminayin Af B'lo Ta'aseh? How do I know you even transgress a
negative prohibition? שנאמר וידבר ה' אל משה לאמר, Shene'emar Vayidaber Hashem El
Moshe Lemor, because it says God spoke to משה Moshe speaking. Oh,
well that answers it. So למימרא דכל פרשה שיש בה לאו, L'meimra
D'chol Parsha Sheyesh Bah Lav, the תורה is talking about a negative
prohibition. Where do you get that from? די רבי יהודה אמר ליה
רבי לבר קפרא, Di Rabbi Yehuda Amar Lei Rabbi L'bar Kappara, so
רבי said to בר קפרא, Bar Kappara, מאי משמע, Mai Mashma, where
do you get it from the verse? אמר ליה דכתיב לאמר, Amar
Lei Dechtiv Lemor, it says לאמר, Lemor, which means לאו נאמר בדברים.
Lav Ne'emar Bidvarim. So there's the לאו, lav, they take out the
למד אלף, lamed aleph, לאמר lemor means לאו lav was said about
these things. Don't do them. בי רבי אמרי, Bei Rabbi Amri, in
the house of רבי they say, לאו אמור, Lav Emur, in לאמר,
lemor, לאו אמור lav emur they were said with a לאו. lav.
Now the question is, what is he talking about? Do you mean
to say that every time the תורה says וידבר ה' אל משה
לאמר, Vayidaber Hashem El Moshe Lemor, that that means that everything that's
a positive מצוה mitzvah also becomes a negative מצוה? mitzvah? So the
שיטה מקובצת Shita Mekubetzet asks this question, and he basically says, well,
what we're, רש"י Rashi sort of emphasized a couple of times, here
that's what it means, here that's what it means. But who tells
you? So the שיטה מקובצת quotes a position that says when we
learn, if it's a פרשה parsha where we learn something should not
be done, but it's only framed in the positive, right, which is
here we learn don't sanctify unblemished to the בדק הבית, Bedek Habayit,
but we only learn it from a positive, and if that פרשה
parsha is introduced with וידבר ה' אל משה לאמר, Vayidaber Hashem El
Moshe Lemor, yes, we also learn a negative prohibition. So the basic
answer is not every time it says it, but every time there's
an implied thing that should not be done, but it's only stated
in the positive, this פסוק וידבר ה' אל משה לאמר Vayidaber Hashem
El Moshe Lemor tells us also a negative prohibition. It's pretty radical.
Normally, either we, even if we say that, we say okay, so
we don't normally פסקן pasken that way, but רש"י Rashi really emphasizes
that for whatever reason this is a very local דרשה. How we
know to only do the דרשה here, I don't know. But here's
the flip side, not only not sanctifying things for a קרבן korban
with a blemish, but not sanctifying unblemished things for the בדק הבית.
Bedek Habayit. Okay, איתמר, Itmar, now let's to wrap this up,
המעלה איברי בעלי מומין Hamaleh Eivarei Ba'alei Mumim or אימורי בעלי מומין
Eimurei Ba'alei Mumim לגבי מזבח, Legabei Mizbe'ach, somebody now not only sanctified
but slaughtered, sprinkled the blood, and also we learned now you cannot
offer up, burn the innards or the limbs if it's an עולה.
olah, That's the question of whether you use איברי, eivarei, which is
the limbs of an עולה, or אימורי, eimurei, the innards if it's
another קרבן. korban, So let's say you did it, we said you
transgressed offering part and offering
all, right, ואשה לא תקריבו מהם, V'isheh Lo Takrivu Mehem, do not
bring a burnt offering from them, even part of them. So אמר
רבא, Amar Rava, so רבא Rava says, עובר משום בל תקטיר כולו
ומשום בל תקטיר מקצתו. Over Mishum Bal Taktir Kulo Umishum Bal Taktir
Miktzato. You transgress offering all of it and offering part of it.
The מהם mehem says don't even burn part of it. So you
have two transgressions, like we said before, there are five prohibitions, two
of them are don't burn part of it, don't burn all of
it.
But if you burnt all of it, you'd be מלקות malkut twice?
Presumably, presumably, and we'll discuss that. אביי אמר, Abaye Amar, אביי Abaye
said, אין לוקין על לאו שבכללות. Ein Lokin Al Lav Shebechlallot. No,
if it's a generic לאו, lav, you don't get lashes. Now, what's
generic? There's a whole discussion how you describe לאו שבכללות. lav shebechlallot.
It includes more than one idea,
and we're not going to obviously figure that all out now, but
the point is here it includes two ideas. Don't burn all, don't
burn part is basically two basic different things wrapped up in one
לאו, lav, you don't get lashes. Now, does he mean you don't
get any lashes? It might mean that according to some opinions, but
it's going to be very clear in this גמרא, here what it
means is you don't get lashes for both aspects of it. If
it's a לאו lav that includes two ideas, you're only going to
get one set of lashes, you're not going to get two sets.
You know, it's here it's even more than a לאו שבכללות. lav
shebechlallot. לאו שבכללות Lav shebechlallot sometimes is a very broad לאו lav
that has multiple different reasons, like the פסוק is לא תאכלו על
הדם, Lo Toachlu Al Hadam, don't eat on the blood. What does
that mean? The גמרא has ten different, you know, very radically different
explanations for that. But here it's actually a subset. Don't burn part
of it is a subset of don't burn all of it. Okay,
so clearly it's
a
לאו. lav. I'll ask you on this. המקדיש בעלי מום לגבי מזבח,
Hamakdish Ba'alei Mum legabei mizbe'ach, we said עובר משום חמישה שמות, over
mishum chamisha shemos, you get five transgressions. תיובתא דאביי, Tiyuvta d'Abaye, he
says you only get four, the last two only count as one.
אמר לך אביי, Amar lach Abaye, Abaye would say בגברי תני. begavrei
tani. We're talking about different people. There are five ways to transgress,
but if I burn all of it, I get one transgression. If
somebody else burns part of it, he gets a transgression. So there
are five prohibitions, but it's not the same person to get all
five. Okay, you don't get double for the last two. So the
גמרא says אי בגברי, ei begavrei, if it's different people that are
doing it, it should say עובר, over, you transgress, it should have
said עוברים מיבעי ליה, ovrim mibaye lei, people can transgress five five
ways. אלא פשיטא בחד גברא. Ela peshita b'chad gavra. We're talking about
one person. תיובתא דאביי, Tiyuvta d'Abaye, a contradiction of Abaye shows that
you will have done five transgressions. אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, Abaye would
say אפיק הקטרת מקצתו ואייתי קבלת הדם. afik haktarat miktzato v'ayti kabalat
hadam. All right, change the text. When it says one of the
transgressions is burning part of it, take that out. It's really say
one of the five is catching the blood. גמרא says, but that's
debated. קבלת הדם לרבי יוסי ברבי יהודה אית ליה. Kabalat hadam l'Rabbi
Yossi b'Rabbi Yehuda it lei. That's the position that comes later, Rabbi
Yossi b'Rabbi Yehuda. לתנא קמא לית ליה. L'Tanna Kamma leit lei. Tanna
Kamma doesn't hold of catching the blood. So he has five without
catching the blood. קשיא. Kashya. All right, it's a problem. לישנא אחרינא,
Lishna achrina, here's another version of that. תהא מידי סיפא רבי יוסי
ברבי יהודה היא דאית ליה קבלת הדם. Tehei midei seifa Rabbi Yossi
b'Rabbi Yehuda hi d'it lei kabalat hadam. Since the end is Rabbi
Yossi b'Rabbi Yehuda of catching the blood, רישא רבנן, reisha Rabbanan, the
beginning is does not include catching the blood, and nevertheless it says
five, and according to Abaye, the last two only count as one,
there's only four. תיובתא דאביי תיובתא. Tiyuvta d'Abaye tiyuvta. That is a
contradiction of Abaye, you are right. So actually here, although it is
really a position which makes a lot of sense, right, that the
part is a subset of all, or actually I should say all
is a subset of part because you transgress the part before you
transgress the anyway, one is a subset of the other and it
makes sense to say it's not two separate prohibitions, actually this text
bears out that you do get two sets of lashes. And let's
at least read the משנה Mishna and we won't start the גמרא
today, but we have about three more minutes, so let's at least
read the next
משנה. Mishna. הכהנים ממירים בשלהם וישראל ממירים בשלהם. Hakohanim memirim beshelahem v'Yisrael
memirim beshelahem. We have two minutes. Kohanim can do תמורה tmura, on
their animals and their קרבנות, if a כהן Kohen. brings a קרבן,
korban, and a ישראל Yisrael does תמורה tmura on his קרבן. korban.
But אין הכהנים ממירים לא בחטאת ולא באשם. ein hakohanim memirim lo
b'chatat v'lo b'asham. And here's the first חידוש, chiddush, that I bring
a קרבן, korban, I give it to a כהן. Kohen Okay, it's
a חטאת, chatat, a sin offering, or it's an אשם. asham. He's
going to be entitled to eat the meat. Maybe he now to
some degree is considered to be the owner of the קרבן. And
now that I've handed it over to him, maybe if he were
to do תמורה, tmura it would be considered an act of תמורה
tmura because now he is entitled to part of the קרבן. Nevertheless,
he can't. In the end, he is bringing my קרבן, not his
קרבן, even if he winds up eating the meat, he's still eating
the meat of my קרבן. And therefore he is never considered the
owner and he cannot transfer, do תמורה tmura on my קרבן. ולא,
and here's the other חידוש, chiddush, ולא בבכור. v'lo bivchor. What happens,
and this is really a חידוש, chiddush, I have a בכור, bechor,
I give it to a כהן. kohen. Who's the owner of this
קרבן? What would you think? Micah, what would you think? I give
my בכור bechor to a כהן. Whose קרבן is it?
Once I give it to him, presumably it's the כהן's.
He now brings it. The חידוש chiddush of this משנה Mishna is
no. It started off as my animal and that's where it became
קדוש kadosh in my house. Even though I'm giving it to him
and he's bringing it alive, it's still considered to be my קרבן,
not his. That is a huge חידוש, chiddush, right? And he cannot
do תמורה tmura on a בכור. bechor. Okay, I'm not even sure
I can change it to say I don't want it. Well, once
it's out of my hands, I might not be able to do
תמורה tmura either. Okay, but but certainly he can't even when it's
in his hands. אמר רבי יוחנן בן נורי, Amar Rabbi Yochanan ben
Nuri, מפני מה אין ממירים בבכור? mipnei mah ein memirim bivchor? Why
not? It's now his. אמר לו רבי עקיבא, Amar lo Rabbi Akiva,
חטאת ואשם מתנה לכהן ובכור מתנה לכהן. chatat v'asham matana l'Kohen uvchor
matana l'Kohen. Let's make a comparison to a חטאת chatat and an
אשם. asham. He's entitled to the meat of a חטאת chatat and
אשם asham and he's entitled to the בכור. bechor. מה חטאת ואשם
אין ממירים בו, Mah chatat v'asham ein memirim bo, the same way
he can't do תמורה tmura by חטאת chatat and אשם, asham, it's
not his, אף בכור אין ממירים בו, af bechor ein memirim bo,
he can't do it by the בכור bechor even though he got
it, he got it as a gift and it basically starts as
the ישראל's. Yisrael So אמר רבי יוחנן בן נורי, Amar Rabbi Yochanan
ben Nuri, Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri did not like this analogy. מה
לי אם אינו ממיר בחטאת ואשם, Mah li im eino memir b'chatat
v'asham, I understand that he can't do it by a חטאת chatat
and an אשם, asham, שאין זוכים בהן בחייהן, she'ein zochim bahen bechayeihen,
he's not entitled to them when they're alive. So when it's offered,
it's mine, the ישראל's Yisrael קרבן, and he only is eating the
meat of my קרבן. So that's not his. תאמר בבכור שזוכים בו
בחייו, Tomar bivchor shezochim bo bechayav, when I give him the בכור,
bechor, the animal was alive and he's the one that brings the
animal to the בית המקדש, so that should be his קרבן, not
mine. One minute. אמר לו רבי עקיבא, Amar lo Rabbi Akiva, Rabbi
Akiva said back, ולא כבר נאמר, v'lo kvar ne'emar, okay, it's a
good point, but the פסוק says, והיה הוא ותמורתו יהיה קדש, v'haya
hu utmurato yihiyeh kodesh, it and the תמורה tmura shall be holy.
היכן קדושה חלה עליו, Heichan kedusha chala alav, so the same way
its sanctity,
the תמורה tmurah occurs in the same place where the original sanctity
occurred. The original sanctity, where did that occur for the בכור? bechor?
בבית בעלים, beveit be'alim, when it was born to my animal. And
since that's where the original sanctity took place, אף תמורה בבית בעלים,
af tmura beveit be'alim, even the act of תמורה takes place. place
in the house of the owners. So it goes where it is
limited to the owner although your logic is a good one, the
source of the קדושה kedusha is sourced with the owner and therefore
only the owner can do a תמורה by a בכור bechor and
not the כהן. We will look at this tomorrow.